<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A clear optick discovering to the eye of reason; that regality is not inconsistent with the ends That episcopacy and presbytery are of the essence That independency is incorporated into the body That levelling is allowable in the constituting [brace] of government. And that the recusants are hugely mistaken in the constitution of their Roman hierarchy. Roughly set out in an humble addresse to the Parliament of England. / By Anthony Norwood, a cordial votary for the peace of the nation.</title>
            <author>Norwood, Anthony.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89748</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1342</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E809_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207599</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866640</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866640</idno>
            <idno type="VID">167917</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89748)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 167917)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 123:E809[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A clear optick discovering to the eye of reason; that regality is not inconsistent with the ends That episcopacy and presbytery are of the essence That independency is incorporated into the body That levelling is allowable in the constituting [brace] of government. And that the recusants are hugely mistaken in the constitution of their Roman hierarchy. Roughly set out in an humble addresse to the Parliament of England. / By Anthony Norwood, a cordial votary for the peace of the nation.</title>
                  <author>Norwood, Anthony.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Mood, and Edward Thomas, and are to be sold at the seven Stars in Pauls Church-yard, and in Green Arbour,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"That regality .. constituting" connected by right bracket on title page.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sep: 5".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Episcopacy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:167917:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A CLEAR OPTICK</hi> DISCOVERING To the EYE of REASON;
<list>
                  <item>That Regality is not inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with the Ends <hi>of Government.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That Epiſcopacy and Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery are of the Eſſence <hi>of Government.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That Independency is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated into the Body <hi>of Government.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>That Levelling is allowable in the conſtituting <hi>of Government.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>And that the Recuſants are hugely miſtaken in the Conſtitution of their Roman Hierarchy.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Roughly ſet out in an humble addreſſe TO THE PARLIAMENT OF ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>By ANTHONY NORWOOD, A cordial Votary for the Peace of the Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Moon,</hi> and <hi>Edward Thomas,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>ſeven Stars</hi> in <hi>Pauls Church-yard,</hi> and in Green <hi>Arbour,</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:167917:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:167917:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable the Speaker of the Parliament of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and to the Earls, Lords, Knights, Gentlemen and Burgeſſes reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, now inveſted by the Suffrage of the People, with the Supream Authority of the Nation.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He reaſonable Caveat of a poor obſcure man may ſometimes ſave a City, and may poſſibly therefore be ſerviceable to a Commonwealth. I owe a duty to my Nation, and muſt either endeavour to perform it, or be condemned of want of Religion and humanity. This hath obliged and emboldned me to tender this Mite as an oblation for the peace and welfare thereof to you the honourable Truſtees of the Nation, by whom the people are in a longing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation to be reſtored to their often promiſed and dearly purchaſed Rights and Liberties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I have been too long a ſad Spectator of thoſe bloudy imbroylments, which have pierced through the Heart of this Nation, whereof I am a ſympathizing Member, and have obſerved that the diverſity of opinions in point of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is that which hath been a principal motive to the mournful Tragedy, and ſtill renders the people unſatisfied and unreconciled. This cauſe being taken away, the effects may happily follow; and therefore I humbly crave
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:167917:3"/>
leave to preſent theſe my ſolitary conceptions upon that ſubject.</p>
            <p>Not to trouble you over long with their vanity who are enemies to all Government, I ſhall only ſay, that albeit it be true, that during the ſhort time that Man continued in his innocency, there was none manifeſtly appearing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then there was no need of any, and none might have been had he continued ſtill in the ſame ſpotleſſe condition: yet ſin being ſince crept into the whole mankinde by the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> to queſtion now whether God doth tolerate and approve of Government, is to queſtion whether he hath left Man power to prevent thoſe infinites of inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, which every day are multiplyed by the growth and overſpreading prevalency of ſin, and by conſequence to draw a ſuſpect upon the Creator, as if he were too unminde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of the preſervation of his own creatures.</p>
            <p>This being blown over, I ſhall now with your patience, endeavour to demonſtrate upon what right the Authority of your Aſſembly is founded, what power you have by virtue of that right, and how invalid their pretences are who ſtand in competition with that right. That ſo the lawfulneſſe and fulneſſe of your Authority being made clear, you may cheerfully proceed in the managing of that truſt which the people of this Nation have repoſed in you, and they reduced to their wonted complyance with your Authority.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> That which hath appeared your moſt eminent oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent is Monarchy, which being by the Abetters truly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined, to be a ſole Government in one without Co-partners or limitation, is totally deſtructive to your Authority: Yet this form of Government (ſay they) is of divine Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination. But he that compares the definition with the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that hath been every where publiſhed by thoſe of that opinion, wherein ſome of them contend, that the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of a Chriſtian Commonwealth ought to be part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Regal, and partly Epiſcopal; otherſome partly Regal and partly Presbyterian, and that both the one and the other (though in the hands of diſtinct and contemporary perſons) are of divine inſtitution, will hardly apprehend
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:167917:3"/>
any ſafety in adhering to a doctrine wherein he findes ſo much contradiction.</p>
            <p>Indeed in the judgement of any conſidering man the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine will ſeem extreamly impertinent, not only becauſe, if it ſhould be admitted that Monarchical Government is of divine Ordination, yet it will reſt diſputable who amongſt infinite millions of men ought to be the only Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch: But alſo becauſe according to their own definition and doctrine, he only can be ſaid to be a Monarch, who, as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> had, hath from God the ſole dominion over the People of all Nations, and in the Beaſts of the field the like ſole propriety; and if it be true of that, or of the Monarchy of <hi>Auguſtus Coeſar,</hi> which comes neereſt to it, which they pretend of others, that they ought to deſcend he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditarily, either the late world knew no lawful Monarchs, if it did, it will be no leſſe lawful to ſubdivide every of them into as many more as they contain families, then to divide thoſe Monarchies into ſo many as are now ſaid to be in Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>This then may be concluded from their own premiſes, that it is as agreeable to the will of God to reduce Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical Government into Families, as to continue it in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths. And this ſeems to be the clear intendment of the inſtitution, aſwell by the example of the ſons of <hi>Noah,</hi> who without regard to the priority of bloud in the elder brother did each of them govern his own family Monarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally; as by that of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who having the advantage of extraordinary illumination, years and bloud, did not take cognizance in a caſe of difference between his own and the ſervants of his Nephew <hi>Lot,</hi> but rather adviſed a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to prevent the growing contention.</p>
            <p>There needs no more to prove, that every Maſter of a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily did or might originally govern his own dependents Monarchically and independently of any other humane authority: the diſpoſing therefore of the world into ſeveral Colonies or Commonwealths compoſed of divers families, cannot truly be taken to be the product of divine Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but of ſome political humane inſtitution, which how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they may probably at the firſt be quartered out by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:167917:4"/>
the violent deciſion of the ſword thirſty after rule and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination; yet where God, who only may diſpenſe with his own laws, made it not lawful by ſome particular known Commiſſion, could not be legally eſtabliſhed, but by the voluntary combination of agreeing families, over every of which the Superiour being by nature independent, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a ſole juriſdiction within his own verge, whoſoever did aſſume a power in prejudice to that right did commit an act inconſiſtent with the end of aſſociating, which main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly regards the preſervation of each incorporated Members propriety, and made himſelf guilty with <hi>Nimrod,</hi> of that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence which was never yet approved by Divinity.</p>
            <p>Be pleaſed to take a ſcantling by a family, wherein, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides only where nature ſeals the obligation, what allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is created is by conſent, as between Maſters and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Husbands and Wives, though that ſex be condemned to ſervitude by God himſelf, and you will eaſily admit that the Maſters ſubjection is not lawfully acquirable up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on lower tearms: for it is too much below reaſon to think that the Superiour is naturally in a more ſervile condition then his ſubordinates; or allowing him the ſame freedom not to allow the ſame rule to hold in Commonwealths, which are but larger copies of that ſmaller Original. And therefore whoſoever hath not a diſpoſition to contend (againſt all right) that the cuſtomary pretences and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of man have power to ſupercede everlaſtingly a poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Law of God, will grant, that the Supream Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of this Nation is of right really and independent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Fatherhood, not to be alienated but by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> For the further manifeſtation of this truth, give me leave to offer to you theſe following reaſons; The firſt drawn from the neceſſity of a known allegiance; that is a neceſſity of knowing that Magiſtrates and ſubordinates have a lawful perſonal relation one to another; and a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of knowing what the power of the one, and duty of the other is being ſo related. And this aſwell in reſpect of the Governour, as of the governed: becauſe as the firſt may ſin by impoſing upon thoſe over whom, and in ſuch caſes
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:167917:4"/>
wherein he hath no warrantable juriſdiction, ſo may the other by betraying their own perſons, liberty or propriety to an obtruded power, or by declining the duty he ows to his real Superior to comply with the more irregular power of an Alien.</p>
            <p>Now amongſt Maſters of Families equally free, indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and uncompellable to aſſociate, who have a ſole and equal juriſdiction over their reſpective ſubordinates, it will be but loſt labour to finde out ſuch an allegiance but by conſent; and this, being paſſed, without limitation, by aſſociated Maſters of families, to ſuch of the Aſſociation, as they eſteem moſt truſty and able to manage publique con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments, convayes to the elected a ſole and independent power over the perſons and eſtates of the Electors, and all thoſe who doe depend upon them, to all intents and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes relating to common accommodation.</p>
            <p>To make out ſuch an Allegiance between a King and a People, or between the Lords and them, in the way where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they uſually claim: is altogether impoſſible; For firſt, they have no warrant to lay a foundation for Government, they cannot lawfully compel people to aſſociate. Next becauſe the Royal pretences are generally drawn from the quality of the Office, that of the Lords for the effects of that qualification, and admitting that every Nation ought to be governed by a King, yet it will reſt queſtionable, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther every King ought to have that latitude of power which may be pretended; and that being allowed will not aſſert the lawfulneſſe of his perſonal calling to that Office, or determine what people are unqueſtionably under his juriſdiction.</p>
            <p>The next is from the nature of municipal laws, by which it is unavoidably neceſſary, for the peaceable being of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry populous Commonwealth, that many actions be made criminal, and many crimes lyable to puniſhment diverſly from what is preſcribed by the finger of God. Such as are many of the ſeveral ſorts of Treaſons, petty Treaſon, Felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, &amp; the like, puniſhable by death, or confiſcation, or both. Some whereof differ little from that of <hi>Shimei</hi> his going over the Brook <hi>Kedron,</hi> for which <hi>Solomon</hi> his King had no
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:167917:5"/>
power to take away his life, had not <hi>Shimei</hi> himſelf firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to forfeit it upon that condition.</p>
            <p>In the making of theſe Laws there is an abſolute neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that the Law-makers have a right of power over the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Eſtates of the whole People of that Nation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are to be executed: becauſe no man may diſpoſe of that wherein he hath not a lawful intereſt. That ſuch a right is not annexed to the Regal Office, is plainly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrable by that ſowre vengeance, which God took upon <hi>Ahab</hi> and his houſe, for tampering to take away the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard and life of his known ſubject <hi>Naboth;</hi> and if Kings have not, neither have the Lords who derive only from Regal Prerogative; and if neither of theſe two have ſuch a right, it remains wholly in the Repreſentatives of the People, and they are the only Law-makers; unleſſe there be ſomething more in the Clergy then in other Chriſtians, which will winde them in upon another ſcore to be ſharers in the ſame Authority. And that (with your patience) comes in the next place to be experimented.</p>
            <p>What claim they lay is ſaid to be derived from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, of whom it is written, that they did not take upon them to diſpoſe of the goods of <hi>Ananias</hi> without his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, nor puniſh the detention without Miracle; and I think that unleſſe they can entitle themſelves to the like qualifications, they will hardly <hi>Ex Officio</hi> prove themſelves competent Law-makers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I remember that Linſy-woolſie garments were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to be worn by the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as thoſe which being compoſed of ingredients of diſcordant and fretting quality, would not endure long in one and the ſame piece. Gods Word is poſitive, that no man can ſerve two maſters. And when I obſerved how wide the rents are which have been every where made in the Church of Chriſt by dividing the polity thereof into Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, and how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle light there is in the Word of God to direct people into a due and ſafe courſe of obedience to each of theſe two ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities reſpectively, I was not apt to think the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to be at all conſiſtent with the wayes of God, or peace of the Nation.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:167917:5"/>
            <p>Yet ſomething they have to ſhoar up the Tradition, and that is the Prieſthood of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which they ſay doth typically relate to theſe Goſpel-times. Which no doubt is true; &amp; let them but ſuſpend their Hierarchy till they can produce one Law made by that Prieſthood whileſt it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in its purity, and I think that will put an end to the buſineſſe. But here ſeems to me to lye the great miſtake: They would have that Nation to be a type of one, or of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Nations only, whereas it was a Type of the whole world; the Levitical Prieſthood repreſenting who are, the reſt of the Tribes who are not of the houſe-hold of faith, who though they be not within the pale, yet are not out of the purlew of the great Foreſt of Chriſt; and though not actually in, yet potentially and in expectancy are of the Church; for the benefits of Chriſts merits are extendable to all, though not taken hold of by all mankinde. And thus between the Type and the Antitype, there hold ſtill due correſpondence, which would not hold ſo currant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if the Type were applyed only to the Chriſtian part of the World: becauſe Chriſt hath made all thoſe Prieſts to God his Father, who have laid hold on him by faith.</p>
            <p>Their ſpiritual Charter of Authority is vacated, if they cannot prove themſelves to be ſolidly inveſted by God with the Prieſthood. And ſince the Son would not ſuffer his Diſciples to forbid that ſtranger to caſt out Devils in his Name, who followed not him their Maſter, me think I may eaſily infer, that no man who is endowed with ſo much grace as to believe all the Articles of faith eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally neceſſary to Salvation, is prohibited by the Father to impede the Devils entrance, by interpoſing thoſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ordinary means which he hath preſcribed. And this not alone in themſelves, but to all others: for love is a general duty, which hath reference to all mankinde; and it is little leſſe then blaſphemy to think that God requires that at mans hand, without giving him a plenary Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to expreſſe it, nor can it be any way ſo well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt as by endeavouring to make people capable of the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of their Saviour. Amongſt Chriſtians then there is none of the <hi>Quorum</hi> in this Commiſſion, and I ſee not how any can be without the approbation and conſent of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:167917:6"/>
their aſſociated fellow-Commiſſioners; and I need not ſay, that the ſame reaſon which holds for Diſcipline that does for Doctrine.</p>
            <p>I might here for a further confirmation of the premiſes, minde you of ſome pertinent Texts in Scripture both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law and in the time of the Goſpel; and ſhew you that before God permitted the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to have Kings, which was upon an emergent occaſion, he gave a general Commiſſion to the People to chuſe them Judges and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in all their Tribes. That <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> two Kings of that Nation, who have left behinde them as good a Character of righteous Government as any, called the people to conſult with them about two buſineſſes of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt importance, the one touching fetching home of the Ark, the other about keeping the Paſſeover. And that the Apoſtles, in taht weighty controverſie concerning Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, adviſed with the Elders and Brethren; and by their approbation ſent letters of reconciliation to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters. Whereby it is manifeſt in what regard the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the People was had in thoſe firſt and beſt ages, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were in ſpiritual or temporal concernments. But I muſt not ſpin out an Epiſtle into a Volume.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> by what hath been already offered to your conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, I ſuppoſe that the neceſſity of a known mutual Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance between Magiſtrates and ſubordinates is made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to you; and I conceive it no leſſe apparent that ſuch an Allegiance cannot be created but by conſent: but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is no truth that meets not with ſome oppoſition, beſides thoſe already mentioned, bear a little longer I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you with my boldneſſe, whileſt I endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move ſome other rubs of a later date, which poſſibly may yet be thought equivalent or ſuperlative to this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe the provident hand of God in ſending down ſo many pregnant bleſſings upon the Army, ſhould be urged as an evidence of Gods pleaſure to confer the right of Authority upon the Inſtruments. To manifeſt that this will not beget that known mutual Allegiance which is neceſſarily inſiſted upon, I ſhall humbly beſeech you to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:167917:6"/>
call to minde that the Parliament did firſt vote the War, and then form and give Commiſſion to the Army. That the People did elect, and thereby give power to the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of that Parliament, and aſſiſt the Army in their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, by their prayers, contributions, and correſpondence. That together with the Commanders, the Infantry and Cavalry bore no inconſiderable ſhare in the great adventure for Liberty; and amongſt all theſe I beleeve you will finde it as hard to determine upon whom Providence hath caſt the lot of Government, as to underſtand by what Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan it was conveyed; and no leſſe difficult to diſcover pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely who are ſubjected to the effects. Many publique ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited men there were, who laboured hard to prepare the way before ever the Parliament could be convened, or the Army march into the field; and not a few under whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, during the long conteſt, God ſent the People ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and ſignal deliverances; and though the good Maſter of the Vine-yard gave as large a ſalary to the laſt comers as to the firſt, yet he gave to all alike.</p>
            <p>I offer this only in relation to thoſe who have not been tainted with Delinquency to the State: for I ſhould not ſpeak my own reaſon, ſhould I ſay that an Army raiſed by Authority of Parliament to protect the Nation hath not power, ſo long as the Government continues unſetled, to uſe all requiſite means to diſcover and prevent clandeſtine machinations, to ſuppreſſe outrages and conſpiracies emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently deſtructive to the Peoples peace, to puniſh thoſe who are convicted offenders, and to hold thoſe under ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection who have forſeited their freedome, by being par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in an offenſive War againſt the Supream Authority of the Nation: for they have appealed to their own ſwords, and being caſt at a Bar of their own chuſing, they cannot truly be ſaid to ſuffer without their own conſents.</p>
            <p>Should it again be ſuppoſed, that, as it hath been of old inſiſted upon by the pretended Clergy, ſome peculiar and ſingular diſpenſation of grace to ſome Chriſtians above other ſome, doth carry with it a right to Soveraignty: I am confident you would not think that this rule will
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:167917:7"/>
reach all thoſe who are endowed with the ſame ſpirit; and I think not infallibly thoſe who are not therewith endowed: becauſe all other graces waiting upon, and receiving their vertue and efficacy through faith, and that being a hidden Myſtery wrapt up in the ſoul of man, and viſible only to the Eye of God, amongſt thoſe who profeſſe to this faith, it is not diſcoverable by any third perſon, who is and who is not capable of the ſame priviledges with real Beleevers.</p>
            <p>I conſeſſe that it is undenyably true, that whoſoever hath a true and lively faith, will ſhew it by his works: but good works (that is, morally good) may be done by thoſe who have no faith. Beſides, if works be the only out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward cognizance of grace, and that of Soveraignty, it may be concluded from the rule of contraries, that ſin denotes a want of grace, and a ſecluding from Soveraignty. And this will be ſo far from begetting a known mutual Allegiance between the Governours and governed, that it will ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſtroy all Government, or tolerate thoſe to be Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours who are void of Grace: becauſe upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, either there will be no more Magiſtrates found to puniſh Malefactors, then there were accuſers remaining to caſt the firſt ſtone at the Adultereſſe, or ſuch only as by profeſſing themſelves to be without ſin do diſclaim any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in a Saviour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> It is not many moneths ſince there came a little pamphlet to my hands, which had ſomething in it not impertinent to the preſent purpoſe, the Author ſaid to be a perſon, who formerly had written a larger Tract in vindication of the power and proceedings of the Peoples late elected Repreſentatives: but in this laſt urgeth that of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi> adviſing them to be obedient to <hi>Nero,</hi> who (without all contradiction) far ſurpaſſed the late King in all kinde of wickedneſſe, as an obligation upon all Chriſtians to ſubmit to that power whatſoever it be under which their lot is fallen. I ſhall leave it to your better judgement to calculate what a huge weight of bloud this doctrine (if it be true) will lay up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the then Parliament, their Army, and all thoſe who
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:167917:7"/>
did adhere or contribute to them, and waving the diſpute as that which hath been the ſubject of many ſatisfactory im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, apply my ſelf only to ſhew how far the Authors opinion goes along with the Premiſes. From whence firſt it may be concluded, that if thoſe primitive Chriſtians, who doubtleſſe had then as much of the Spirit, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by as great priviledges as any ſince their times, were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by the Apoſtle to ſubmit to an Infidel power, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the gifts of the Spirit do not render the Receivers unqueſtionably capable of command.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He acknowledgeth that if <hi>Nero</hi> had attained the Throne by the ſuffrage of the people, it had been more orderly then by the Senate, which it ſeems by him was not ſo elected; and if by the Senate leſſe diſorderly, then by the artifice of his mother, and help of the Cohorts and reſt of the Souldiery. All this comes very neer to what I have delivered. And had he not been ſhort of telling his Readers of the ſin that <hi>Nero</hi> committed by falling upon the moſt diſorderly way of the three, he had fully juſtified my ſaying; for I endevour to maintain, that the right to chuſe their own Magiſtrates is in the people, and if it be granted that he that takes upon him to ſuperintend them without their conſent, is guilty of ſinne, their right is fully aſſerted.</p>
            <p>If not in <hi>Nero</hi> an Infidel, yet to uſurp a power upon a ſelf-account is certainly a ſin in a Chriſtian, and that not of the ſmaller ſize: yet I will not determine that that Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture in the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> wherein the Man of ſin is ſaid to ſit in the Temple of God as God, may in a degree be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to any perſons, who being Members of Chriſts Church, do under the pretence of ſome peculiar divine diſpenſation, exerciſe a coercive juriſdiction over their brethren of the ſame faith, though that in <hi>Peter,</hi> wherein Chriſtians are forbidden to Lord it over Gods inheritance, ſeems very much to countenance the application: But I may ſay, and yet preach no falſe doctrine, that it is not the vocall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation, but the actuall prelation or Prelating that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts the guilt.</p>
            <p>Be this the ſenſe of the Holy Ghoſt or be it not, it had
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:167917:8"/>
not been unworthy the late ſelf-voters ſerious thoughts to conſider, whether he that makes a Law to compell others to pay Subſidies and Contributions, or to hazard their lives in the face of an enemy, or by which any other is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of his Liberty, Goods, Lands, or Life for counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting the publique coyne or Seals, do not thereby com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a ſin little inferiour to that of <hi>Ahab,</hi> and make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf obnoxious to the like puniſhment, unleſſe he have ſome ſuch warrant as <hi>Solomon</hi> had to take away the life of his ſubject <hi>Shimei.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Liberty hath been proclaimed, which, amongſt aſſociated people, who muſt live under a Law, conſiſts only in the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of electing Law-makers. Indeed conſent is that alone that takes the ſtain of oppreſſion and antichriſtian uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion out of the authority of Chriſtian Magiſtrates. It is the ſpring that gives motion to all the wheels in the Watch of National Government. And whether the caſe of Government be handled under a Civil or under an Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical notion, your Authority ſpringing from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the people, ſtill remains the ſame ſole and intire, without any dependency or commixture, what pretences ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever have been interpoſed. The peoples independent power is conſigned over to you, by which you are inveſted as well with the Supreme as with the Legiſlative power, for they are twins not to be ſeparated, but by a mutual and total Annihilation. This is the authority and priviledge of Parliament; and you are the Guardians of this Priviledge and Authority. If it miſcarry through your default, you fail in your Truſt, and the ſin will lye at your own door.</p>
            <p>You need not object the want of Preſidents, you have the example of the peoples laſt Repreſentatives, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauntedly acted by theſe juſtifiable Principles, and were cheerfully ſeconded by the people with liberal Contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. You have the concurrence of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> nation before it was ſeduced; and the agreement and cooperation of the Commanders in chief, and of the reſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, Officers and Souldiers of both Armies. You have the ſame Army ſtill under the ſame Commanders, who
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:167917:8"/>
would not certainly have ingaged ſo deep in the quarrel, had they not been fully ſatisfied of the juſtneſs of the Cauſe. And therefore ſeeing your authority is the ſame, and that you are not convened without their approbation, to fear to proceed upon the ſame juſt and honourable principles, were to ſeem to ſuſpect them of the ignominious crime of Apoſtaſie, and that would be taken as ill, as to tell a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier that he is run from his colours.</p>
            <p>You have had a fair Copy ſet you, and the people will have little cauſe to give you thanks, if you ſuffer it to be fullied in your tranſcribing. By their inſiſting upon their own power the Lawes of the land are rendred more au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritative: for the legiſlative power being ſolely in the Repreſentatives of the People, there wanted not cauſe to apprehend that all the former Statutes and Charters of this Commonwealth, not excepting <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> or any other Statute or Charter whatſoever, being hammered out under a kinde of controlment of Kings and Lords Spirituall and Temporal, who ſeldome were remiſſe to improve their own pretentions, were (if not illegitimate and invalid, yet) not vertual enough to prevent unquiet expoſtulations; and whatſoever virulent and exaſperated tongues may ſuggeſt, poſterity will entertain it as an act of prudence, juſtice and honour in your Predeceſſors, who were intruſted with the intereſt of the people, to free the legiſlative power out of the former Wardſhip, and to reaſſume it to themſelves, by whoſe ſole authority the Lawes and Statutes of the Nation might be tendred leſſe ſubject to querulous cenſure, and more obliging.</p>
            <p>As it is in making, ſo it is in executing of Lawes, the power by which they are executed will be doubtfull and controvertable, if it be not derived from the clear ſtream of the peoples conſent. This was plainly experimented the late Kings caſe, whoſe claim being of another nature, and his title and power therefore uncertain, fill'd the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion full of conſuming diſſenſions. Whereas had he inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only upon the conſent of the people, he might have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the peace of the Nation, reſcued his perſon and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from thoſe ſharp encounters under which they have
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:167917:9"/>
ſince ſuffered, and ſecured his office from that hideous ſtorm with which it was at laſt overwhelmed: for had he owned his inveſtiture from the People, by which all thoſe litigations that cauſed the diſtempers had been removed, the Regall office (beſides that it had the truſt of ſeeing the Lawes duly executed) being military, and ſo taken to be in the ſenſe of Scripture, there was no cauſe why it ſhould be thought an office prohibited by God, or why the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement of a title ſhould make wiſe men ſtumble at ſo neceſſary a ſupplement to their own defence and ſafety.</p>
            <p>But no title would ſerve turn, but divine right, and that mounting him upon too elevating wings, precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated him to deſtruction; and prevailed with his adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, apprehending thereby ſomething in his perſon or office, above the ordinary pitch of humanity, to hazard their perſons and eſtates in a war againſt that authority, againſt which had they prevailed, they had fought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into ſuch a ſervitude, as their own vaſſals will not brook to hear of without regret and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The very ſame Simple was found out, aſwell by the Epiſcopall as by the Presbyterian party, and each of them apply'd it as a cordiall to their Eccleſiaſticall polity. You will beſt judge of the vertue, if you pleaſe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the operation. That you may ſee how low they have brought it, give me leave to uncaſe this their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient.</p>
            <p>Grant they muſt, that the primitive Chriſtians had within themſelves a peculiar kinde of Government, or elſe their inſiſting upon the like in the preſent Church is meerly idle, and they cannot make any pretence to any Government peculiar to Chriſtians of the firſt ages, but what was in their hands who were diſtinguiſhed by the denominations of Biſhops, Presbyters, or Elders and Deacons. So that although all of theſe did or might preach, yet their office was not Doctrinal but Diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary. And this I ſhall endevour to make further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by theſe reaſons. Firſt, becauſe they were approved
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:167917:9"/>
fit for thoſe Offices by their known care and skill to govern well their own families. Next, becauſe the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Apoſtle to chuſe ſome to officiate in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments relating to diſcipline, to the end, that they who were ſet apart for Doctrine, might not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn from that more neceſſary duty, would have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted them alſo from any office of that nature, had thoſe Biſhops and the reſt been of the Doctrinall order.</p>
            <p>They were then no more but civill Magiſtrates in a Chriſtian colony; and I think that the Government of this Nation by a Repreſentative Councel of the Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, wherein the Speaker may be properly termed the Biſhop, Superintendent or Prelate, and the reſt of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers the Elderſhip or Presbytery, is not at all different from that of the primitive Churches, ſave only in the variation of title, which, though it hath made a huge noiſe in the Chriſtian world, are no more but the ſame ſenſe in a different dialect.</p>
            <p>It is as poſſible to ſtop water from returning to its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Center, as to dam up authority from the Sea of the people. But the opinion of holineſſe dazles the eyes of wiſe men. It will caſt a ſad reflection upon the ſoule of every ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hearted Chriſtian, who is no enemy to the unity and proſperity of this Nation, when he conſiders how many of her natives, men of able and active parts, who might therefore be of ſingular uſe to this Common-wealth, have made themſelves uncapable of being imployed in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agery of publique affairs, and of joyning together in Communion with their brethren of the ſame faith and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by drawing counter to a milde and warrantable Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, in the more rigid and chargeable yoke of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Hierarchy, that hath not whereupon to lay a foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but what hath been here expreſt.</p>
            <p>The attribute of holineſſe is common to all Beleevers; and, although in the primitive times, when Chriſtians were under a twofold kinde of Government, the one pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to themſelves, the other Emperial and in common
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:167917:10"/>
with them to all other people under that juriſdiction, they might make uſe of the terme, to diſtinguiſh between their own and the Emperial polity, yet being in that point now all equal, their polity cannot be otherwiſe formed but by moral and prudential Principles, which had it been ſo underſtood, would have long agoe reconciled the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Recuſants to the Engliſh Diſcipline; and the non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conforming Proteſtants to thoſe indifferent things of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and order, which have been heretofore bogled at as ſuperſtitious and idolatrous, in regard they were ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the ſuſpicious ſpots of imputative ſanctity.</p>
            <p>This, together with the activity of the Miniſtry in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truding themſelves into diſciplinary negotiations, is that which hath wrought the Office into diſtaſt with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but were this Remora removed, and they content to conform themſelves to the Apoſtles Rule, not to leave the Word of God to ſerve tables, I cannot think that in this Common-wealth, any ingenuous man would ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine it leſſe convenient to have a ſetled Miniſtery for all publique oratories, then to have Judges ſelected from amongſt others of the ſame profeſſion to ſit in places of judicature, as that which is providentially neceſſary to avoid confuſion where there is a parity. And thus the quarrellings about the ordination and maintenance of Miniſters, together with thoſe formal accommodations, which do pertain to their officiating, may receive a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory compoſure, being taken only as civill inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and regulated by the Repreſentatives of the nation, who by the unlimited conſent of the people intereſted in all capacities, are qualified to preſcribe, aſwell unpreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dented formes of adminiſtration in publique devotions, as unexampled puniſhments for new coyned crimes; and with the ſame obligation upon the conſciences of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters.</p>
            <p>Some object that the <hi>Galatians</hi> had Congregations inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent one of another, which were accounted and called Churches, and therefore they think that national Churches are not allowable. What then? A Parliamentary power
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:167917:10"/>
they acknowledge. Muſt then every Congregation or Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis ſmell of the old leaven, and have within it ſelf an Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical juriſdiction? Admit they muſt. From whence comes this Juriſdiction, but from the conſent of the parties congregated? and by the like conſent it is conveyed again to the Repreſentatives of the Nation, by which they are inveſted with their ſole power, unleſſe they can produce ſome clauſe of reſervation.</p>
            <p>But truly I conceive their allegation will not hold: for it is plain that in the firſt ages, there were Churches in private houſes, which by their own confeſſion did not goe againſt Gods order in forming themſelves into Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations; and to enlarge Congregations into National Churches, ſeems not to be leſſe agreeable to his pleaſure: becauſe it comes neerer to that great deſign of God, to bring all true Beleevers into one fold under one Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard Chriſt Jeſus. And therefore this of the <hi>Galatians</hi> I conceive to be cauſed by the interpoſition of their cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumferencing neighbours, who being Infidels hindered that free intercourſe and Communion, which had been more agreeable to their profeſſion.</p>
            <p>What ſhould I ſay more? You are the independent Presbytery or Elderſhip of this Claſſis or Congregation of the Chriſtian World, who have the ſole power of making and repealing Laws, and of placing and diſplacing ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Officers, whether Magiſterial or Miniſterial, as ſhall in your judgements ſeem moſt conducing to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique accommodation. And this form of Government wherein the native equality and liberty of every indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual Member of this Commonwealth is indifferently and unanimouſly ſubmitted to perſons elected by themſelves, for the advancement of every mans private together with the publique intereſt, may (beſides thoſe that I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready run over) fully ſatisfie the Levelling party, who have as well an equall freedome to elect, as an equall poſſibility to be the elected; except their deſign runs ſo high, as an aym to caſt all ſublunary bleſſings into one joynt ſtock, for an equal benefit to all mankinde; and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:167917:11"/>
if this be their plot (though it were the way to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore me to the capacity of eating daily bread, yet) I muſt not bear a part in it: becauſe the command of God to relieve the poore is a void command, if in the Goods of this world they have a right to an equall proportion; nor may it be admitted that God forbids not Man to cover his neighbours, but his own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety.</p>
            <p>Thus have I wound my ſelf out of the maze of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Government aſſiſted by the clew of Conſent. And now (me thinks) I might more properly call it a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Directory, inſtructing aſſociated families to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in an honeſt and peaceable correſpondence one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another for publique preſervation; and this drawn out by their own Repreſentatives, preſcribing civil rules, and ordaining Officers aſwell to ſee thoſe rules obſerved, as to puniſh offenders according to the rules by them preſcribed, wherein there is no injury or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion, becauſe acted by conſent, which being volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary layes upon every man an equall obligation; and theſe rules being repealable by the Truſtees of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and by what titles ſoever thoſe Magiſtrates who are by them conſtituted, are diſtinguiſhed, the power of the people is not taken away, but they continue ſtill the Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerents under Chriſt their King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> What deſolations have befallen this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth by the fatal diviſions which happened amongſt the Members of the late elected Parliament, cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred without a ſad reſentment; and it is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that ſome of thoſe different opinions, which have hitherto nouriſhed private animoſities amongſt the people, may yet have too great a reflection upon your Aſſembly. Your unity may binde up theſe wounds; and truly in this which I have offered to that end, I ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing deviating from the Will of God, or inconſiſtent with the juſt ends of Government; and therefore not the Jeſſe likely to be inſtrumental to concord.</p>
            <p>It is the reſtraining of ſin, and a tendency to his glory,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:167917:11"/>
that renders National Government accepted with God. There is a failer in both theſe, if Government be not built up upon a juſt and right foundation; and ſin ſeldom draws along with it Gods protection. Juſtice exalteth a Nation, but ſin is a ſhame to any People, is the aphoriſm of the wiſeſt <hi>Solomon.</hi> Beſides that it cannot be without ſin, this Nation hath experimentally felt that two coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoyſing powers in one politique, is as monſtrous as a heart and a heart in one natural body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> My zeal for God and my Nation hath made me too much a treſpaſſer upon your patience. But proſperity flowes there, where righteouſneſſe and peace doe kiſſe each other. This is the object of my prayers, this the object of my wiſhes, this the object of my endevours, and this is that which hath drawn upon you the trouble of this rude pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment. I have heard the ſad complaints of the People who juſtly cry out for redreſſe, and I deſpair not of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome healing applications. I know that the many tempeſtuous counter blaſts, which have broken in upon this Nation, have driven in before them exaſperating ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regularities. But let him that expects a ſtrict obſervance of rule amidſt ſuch high diſtractions, betake himſelf to frame ſome curious maſter-piece, in the main top of a ſhip toſſed with ahideous ſtorm, conſtant in no point of the Compaſſe, and there try what credit he can get by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking. The rigor of the Law is often injurious, where it meets not with ſome qualification. In thoſe actions which are not ſteered in a direct courſe, neceſſity excuſeth the Pilot, if they be directed to a right Haven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I have heard that one of the braveſt Generals that ever commanded the <hi>Roman</hi> Legions, after he had victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly aſſerted the peoples liberty, and put an end to a Civil war, offered up his power and Commiſſion to the then aſſembled Senate, by whom he was re-inveſted and gratified with more triumphant dignities. Here was a fair and honorable correſpondence. And this procured a preſent and laſting peace to that Empire, and rendered it flouriſhing and formidable.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:167917:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I have now diſcharged my Conſcience without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, without partiality, without prejudice. Your buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is great, Your truſt great, I have now no more to doe but to proſtrate my ſelf at the feet of him who is the Fountain of all goodneſſe, humbly praying that he will direct you in all your conſultations to reflect ſtill upon his glory, the ſalvation of your own ſouls, and the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and welfare of this disjoynted Nation. This will draw down the bleſſings of Heaven upon your endevours. And for this ſhall be the daily oblations of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours poor Orator And humble Servant <hi>Anthony Norwood.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
